Guide to the Voices of the Children Footage and Transcripts
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Voices of the Children footage and transcripts
1995-1996
MS 1737
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
11
(86 boxes)
The materials consist of motion picture footage (on videotape) created during the filming of Voices of the Children, an Emmy-award winning documentary film about three individuals who as children survived imprisonment in the Terezi?n (Theresienstadt) concentration camp in the Czech Republic. The videotapes include interviews and supplementary footage, transcripts, and indexes. Interviewees include Michael Kraus, Ela Weissberger, Rafael Sommer, Helga Kinsky, and their families.
Terezín Foundation
Justman, Zuzana
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the Terezi?n Foundation, 1998.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy for their personal use should consult Copying Services information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
Biographical / Historical
Zuzana Justman, president of the Terezi?n Foundation, wrote and directed Voices of the Children. Justman was born in Czechoslovakia in 1931 and survived two years in the Terezi?n (Theresienstadt) concentration camp. She left Czechoslovakia in 1948. She received a B.A. from Vassar and a Ph.D. from Columbia University. She is a writer and filmmaker.
Scope and Contents
The materials consist of motion picture footage (on videotape) created during the filming of Voices of the Children, an Emmy-award winning documentary film about three individuals who survived imprisonment in the Terezi?n (Theresienstadt) concentration camp in the Czech Republic. The videotapes include interviews and supplementary footage, transcripts, and indices. Interviewees include Michael Kraus, Ela Weissberger, Rafael Sommer, Helga Kinsky and their families.
Voices of the Children relates the experiences of three survivors, Helga Hosková Michael Kraus, and Helga Kinsky, who were imprisoned as children in the Terezi?n (Theresienstadt) concentration camp. Zuzana Justman, president of the Terezi?n Foundation and a survivor of two years in the camp, wrote and directed the film. She documents the children's incarceration through the use of their personal journals and drawings. She follows their stories through the postwar years to present day, filming the survivors with their families as they explore the effect of the Holocaust on their lives.
Arrangement
The materials are arranged by creator-assigned tape number.
Holocaust survivors -- Interviews; Holocaust, Jewish (1939-1945) -- Czech Republic -- Personal narratives; Hoskova, Helga; Justman, Zuzana; Pollak-Kinsky, Helga, 1930-; Kraus, Michael; Terezín Foundation; Theresienstadt (Concentration camp)
- Michael Kraus and family
  - Tape #1, CR #1-2
    - Complete footage, 1995; 1 videotape (Betacam-SP), 23:37 minutes (Box 1)
    - Michael Kraus diaries, after the war, Circa 1995; 1 (Box 2)
    - Transcript: Michael Kraus, Circa 1995 (Box 86, Folder 1)
  - Tape #2, CR #3-4
    - Complete footage, 1995; 1 videotape (Betacam-SP), 23:30 minutes (Box 3)
    - Michael Kraus interview continued on sofa, Circa 1995; 1 (Box 4)
    - Transcript: Michael Kraus, Circa 1995 (Box 86, Folder 2)
  - Tape #3, CR #5-6
    - Complete footage, 1995; 1 videotape (Betacam-SP), 23:37 minutes (Box 5)
    - Michael Kraus interview at table, Circa 1995; 1 (Box 6)
    - Transcript: Michael Kraus, Circa 1995 (Box 86, Folder 3)
  - Tape #4, CR #7-8
    - Complete footage, 1995; 1 videotape (Betacam-SP), 23:39 minutes (Box 7)
    - Michael Kraus interview at table, Circa 1995; 1 (Box 8)
    - Transcript: Michael Kraus, Circa 1995 (Box 86, Folder 4)
  - Tape #5, CR #9-10
    - Complete footage, 1995; 1 videotape (Betacam-SP), 23:38 minutes (Box 9)
    - Michael Kraus interview at table, Circa 1995; 1 (Box 10)
    - Transcript: Michael and Ilana Kraus, Circa 1995 (Box 86, Folder 5)
  - Tape #6, CR #11-12
    - Complete footage, 1995; 1 videotape (Betacam-SP), 22:19 minutes (Box 11)
    - Ilana Kraus and Michael Kraus at the office, Circa 1995; 1 (Box 12)
    - Transcript: Ilana and Michael Kraus, Circa 1995 (Box 86, Folder 6)
  - Tape #7, CR #13-14
    - Complete footage, 1995; 1 videotape (Betacam-SP), 22:42 minutes (Box 13)
    - Michael Kraus interview in office; cooking; sweeping leaves; Dana arrives, Dana on bicycle, Boston Holocaust Memorial, Circa 1995; 1 (Box 14)
    - Transcript: Michael Kraus, Ela Weissberger, Dana Kraus, Circa 1995 (Box 86, Folder 7)
  - Tape #8, CR #15-16
    - Complete footage, 1995; 1 videotape (Betacam-SP), 22:46 minutes (Box 15)
    - Cooking, Michael Kraus on potatoes; Michael, Ilana and Dana Kraus at table, lunch verité, Circa 1995; 1 (Box 16)
  - Tape #9, CR #17-18
    - Complete footage, 1995; 1 videotape (Betacam-SP), 22:46 minutes (Box 17)
    - Lunch verité continued; interview with Dana Kraus, Circa 1995; 1 (Box 18)
    - Transcript: Dana Kraus, Circa 1995 (Box 86, Folder 8)
  - Tape #10, CR #19-20
    - Complete footage, 1995; 1 videotape (Betacam-SP), 22:42 minutes (Box 19)
    - Interviews: Michael Kraus in kitchen, at computer, Circa 1995; 1 (Box 20)
    - Transcript: Michael Kraus, Circa 1995 (Box 86, Folder 9)
  - Tape #11, CR #21-22
    - Complete footage, 1995; 1 videotape (Betacam-SP), 22:51 minutes (Box 21)
    - Michael Kraus: diary readings, photographs, Boston Holocaust Memorial, Circa 1995; 1; This videocassette has loss of video at 00:22:30, but audio continues. Then, towards the end of the recording, the original tape, from which this dub comes from proceeds to go into rewind. (Box 22)
    - Transcript: Michael Kraus, Circa 1995 (Box 86, Folder 10)
  - Tape #12, CR #23-24
    - Complete footage, 1995; 1 videotape (Betacam-SP), 22:47 minutes (Box 23)
    - Transcript: Michael Kraus, Circa 1995 (Box 86, Folder 11)
  - Tape #13, CR #25-26
    - Complete footage, 1995; 1 videotape (Betacam-SP), 22:53 minutes (Box 24)
    - Michael Kraus diary reading, final interview, Circa 1995; 1 (Box 25)
    - Transcript: Michael Kraus, Circa 1995 (Box 86, Folder 12)
  - Tape #14, CR #27-28
    - Complete footage, 1995; 1 videotape (Betacam-SP), 22:13 minutes (Box 26)
    - Michael Kraus interview, photographs, drawings, Kamarad, circa 1995; 1 (Box 27)
    - Transcript: Michael Kraus, Circa 1995 (Box 86, Folder 13)
  - Tape #15, CR #29-30
    - Complete footage, 1995; 1 videotape (Betacam-SP), 23:37 minutes (Box 28)
    - Michael Kraus family photographs, diary drawings, Circa 1995; 1 (Box 29)
  - Transcripts of excerpts from Michael Kraus interviews, Circa 1995 (Box 86, Folder 18)
- Ela Weissberger
  - Tape #16, CR #31-32
    - Complete footage, 1995; 1 videotape (Betacam-SP), 22:27 minutes (Box 30)
    - Interview, Circa 1995; 1 (Box 31)
    - Transcript, Circa 1995 (Box 86, Folder 14)
  - Tape #17, CR #33
    - Complete footage, 1995; 1 videotape (Betacam-SP), 11:35 minutes (Box 32)
    - Interview, Circa 1995; 1 (Box 33)
    - Transcript, Circa 1995 (Box 86, Folder 15)
  - Tape #18, CR #34-35
    - Complete footage, 1995; 1 videotape (Betacam-SP), 21:08 minutes (Box 34)
    - Interview, Circa 1995; 1 (Box 35)
    - Transcript, Circa 1995 (Box 86, Folder 16)
- Unidentified subjects
  - Tape #19, T.C.: 19:00 hr., Complete footage, 1995; 1 videotape (Betacam-SP), 23:25 minutes (Box 36)
  - Tape #20, T.C.: 20:00 hr., Complete footage, 1995; 1 videotape (Betacam-SP), 21:30 minutes (Box 37)
- Rafael Sommer
  - Tape #21, CR #5-6
    - Complete footage, 1995; 1 videotape (Betacam-SP), 23:37 minutes (Box 38)
    - Transcript, Circa 1995 (Box 86, Folder 17)
- Unidentified subjects
  - Tape #22, CR #7-8, Complete footage, 1995; 1 videotape (Betacam-SP), 23:37 minutes (Box 39)
  - Tape #23, CR #9-10, Complete footage, 1995; 1 videotape (Betacam-SP), 23:38 minutes (Box 40)
  - Tape #24, T.C.: 01:00 hr., Complete footage, 1995; 1 videotape (Betacam-SP), 23:40 minutes (Box 41)
  - Tape #25, T.C.: 02:00 hr., 1995; 1 videotape (Betacam-SP), 14:48 minutes (Box 42)
- Helga Hosková and family
  - Tape #26, T.C.: 03:00 hr.
    - Complete footage, 1995; 1 videotape (Betacam-SP), 24:17 minutes (Box 43)
    - Transcript: Helga Hosková, Circa 1995 (Box 86, Folder 22)
  - Tape #27, T.C.: 04:00 hr.
    - Complete footage, 1995; 1 videotape (Betacam-SP), 24:24 minutes (Box 44)
    - Transcript: Helga Hosková, Circa 1995 (Box 86, Folder 23)
  - Tape #28, T.C.: 05:00 hr.
    - Complete footage, 1995; 1 videotape (Betacam-SP), 23:53 minutes (Box 45)
    - Transcript: Helga Hosková, Circa 1995 (Box 86, Folder 24)
  - Tape #29, T.C.: 06:00 hr.
    - Complete footage, 1995; 1 videotape (Betacam-SP), 23:52 minutes (Box 46)
    - Transcript: Helga Hosková, Circa 1995 (Box 86, Folder 25)
  - Tape #30, T.C.: 07:00 hr.
    - Complete footage, 1995; 1 videotape (Betacam-SP), 22:35 minutes (Box 47)
    - Transcript: Helga Hosková, Circa 1995 (Box 86, Folder 26)
  - Tape #31, T.C.: 08:00 hr.
    - Complete footage, 1995; 1 videotape (Betacam-SP), 24:14 minutes (Box 48)
    - Transcript: Helga Hosková, Circa 1995 (Box 86, Folder 27)
  - Tape #32, T.C.: 09:00 hr.
    - Complete footage, 1995; 1 videotape (Betacam-SP), 24:00 minutes (Box 49)
    - Transcript: Helga Hosková, Circa 1995 (Box 86, Folder 28)
  - Tape #33, T.C.: 10:00 hr.
    - Complete footage, 1995; 1 videotape (Betacam-SP), 24:14 minutes (Box 50)
    - Transcript: Helga Hosková, Circa 1995 (Box 86, Folder 29)
  - Tape #34, T.C.: 11:00 hr., Complete footage, 1995; 1 videotape (Betacam-SP), 16:48 minutes (Box 51)
  - Tape #35, T.C.: 12:00 hr.
    - Complete footage, 1995; 1 videotape (Betacam-SP), 23:48 minutes (Box 52)
    - Transcript: Katka Komasová, Helga Hosková, Circa 1995 (Box 86, Folder 30)
  - Tape #36, T.C.: 13:00 hr., Complete footage, 1995; 1 videotape (Betacam-SP), 11:24 minutes (Box 53)
  - Tape #37, T.C.: 14:00 hr.
    - Complete footage, 1995; 1 videotape (Betacam-SP), 23:44 minutes (Box 54)
    - Transcript: Helga Hosková, Circa 1995 (Box 86, Folder 31)
  - Tape #38, T.C.: 15:00 hr.
    - Complete footage, 1995; 1 videotape (Betacam-SP), 24:00 minutes (Box 55)
    - Transcript: Katka Komasová, Helga Hosková, Circa 1995 (Box 86, Folder 32)
  - Tape #39, T.C.: 16:00 hr., Complete footage, 1995; 1 videotape (Betacam-SP), 23:44 minutes (Box 56)
  - Tape #40, T.C.: 17:00 hr.
    - Complete footage, 1995; 1 videotape (Betacam-SP), 23:31 minutes (Box 57)
    - Transcript: Jiri Hosek, Marie Hosková, Circa 1995 (Box 86, Folder 33)
  - Partial translation (Czech to English) of interview with Helga Hosková and her family, Circa 1995 (Box 86, Folder 34)
- Unidentified subjects
  - Tape #41, T.C.: 18:00 hr., Complete footage, 1995; 1 videotape (Betacam-SP), 12:46 minutes (Box 58)
  - Tape #42, T.C.: 19:00 hr., Complete footage, 1995; 1 videotape (Betacam-SP), 27:18 minutes (Box 59)
  - Tape #43, T.C.: 20:00 hr., Complete footage, 1995; 1 videotape (Betacam-SP), 21:31 minutes (Box 60)
- Helga Kinsky and family
  - Tape #44, T.C.: 21:00 hr., Complete footage, 1995; 1 videotape (Betacam-SP), 22:25 minutes (Box 61)
  - Transcript: Helga Kinsky, Circa 1995 (Box 86, Folder 35)
  - Tape #45, T.C.: 22:00 hr.
    - Complete footage, 1995; 1 videotape (Betacam-SP), 23:47 minutes (Box 62)
    - Transcript: Helga Kinsky, Circa 1995 (Box 86, Folder 36)
  - Tape #46
    - Complete footage, 1995; 1 videotape (Betacam-SP), 12:41 minutes (Box 63)
    - Transcript: Helga Kinsky, Circa 1995 (Box 86, Folder 37)
  - Tape #47
    - Complete footage, 1995; 1 videotape (Betacam-SP), 22:44 minutes (Box 64)
    - Transcript: Helga Kinsky, Circa 1995 (Box 86, Folder 38)
  - Tape #48
    - Complete footage, 1995; 1 videotape (Betacam-SP), 22:42 minutes (Box 65)
    - Transcript: Helga Kinsky, Erik Kinsky, Circa 1995 (Box 86, Folder 39)
  - Tape #49
    - Complete footage, 1995; 1 videotape (Betacam-SP), 22:42 minutes (Box 66)
    - Transcript: Erik Kinsky, Circa 1995 (Box 86, Folder 40)
  - Tape #50
    - Complete footage, 1995; 1 videotape (Betacam-SP), 24:13 minutes (Box 67)
    - Transcript: Erik Kinsky, Frieda Kafka, Helga Kinsky, Circa 1995 (Box 86, Folder 41)
  - Tapes #49-50, Interview with Erik Kinsky, Circa 1995; 1 (Box 68)
    - Use copy, 1 (Box 68U)
  - Tape #51
    - Complete footage, 1995; 1 videotape (Betacam-SP), 22:40 minutes (Box 69)
    - Transcript: Helga Kinsky, Circa 1995 (Box 86, Folder 42)
  - Tape #52
    - Complete footage, 1995; 1 videotape (Betacam-SP), 22:50 minutes (Box 70)
    - Transcript: Helga Kinsky, Circa 1995 (Box 86, Folder 43)
  - Tape #53
    - Complete footage, 1995; 1 videotape (Betacam-SP), 23:54 minutes (Box 71)
    - Transcript: Helga Kinsky, Circa 1995 (Box 86, Folder 44)
  - Tape #54
    - Complete footage, 1995; 1 videotape (Betacam-SP), 24:25 minutes (Box 72)
    - Interview with Eva Kinsky, Circa 1995; 1 (Box 73)
      - Use copy, 1 (Box 73U)
    - Transcript: Eva Kinsky, Helga Kinsky, Circa 1995 (Box 86, Folder 45)
  - Tape #55
    - Complete footage, 1995; 1 videotape (Betacam-SP), 23:41 minutes (Box 74)
    - Transcript: Helga Kinsky, Circa 1995 (Box 86, Folder 46)
  - Tape #56
    - Complete footage, 1995; 1 videotape (Betacam-SP), 23:50 minutes (Box 75)
    - Transcript: Helga Kinsky, Circa 1995 (Box 86, Folder 47)
  - Tape #57
    - Complete footage, 1995; 1 videotape (Betacam-SP), 23:55 minutes (Box 76)
    - Transcript: Helga Kinsky, Circa 1995 (Box 86, Folder 48)
  - Tape #58, Complete footage, 1995; 1 videotape (Betacam-SP), 24:15 minutes (Box 77)
  - Tape #59, Complete footage, 1995; 1 videotape (Betacam-SP), 23:59 minutes (Box 78)
  - Tape #60, Complete footage, 1995; 1 videotape (Betacam-SP), 12:56 minutes (Box 79)
  - Tape #61, Complete footage, 1995; 1 videotape (Betacam-SP), 24:08 minutes (Box 80)
  - Tape #62, Complete footage, 1995; 1 videotape (Betacam-SP), 23:05 minutes (Box 81)
  - Tapes #1005-1006, Interview with Eva Kinsky (track only), Circa 1995; 1 (Box 82)
    - Use copy, 1 (Box 82U)
  - Transcript of interview in German with Eva Kinsky and English translation (film source unidentified), Circa 1995 (Box 86, Folder 49)
- Assemblies
  - Rough assembly, Michael Kraus, 1995 November 27; 1 (Box 83)
  - Helga Hosková rough assembly, 1995 December 9; 1 (Box 84)
  - Helga Kinsky assembly, Circa 1995; 1 (Box 85)
- Indices
  - U.S. material B-roll index, Circa 1995 (Box 86, Folder 19)
  - Helga Hosková B-rolls index, Circa 1995 (Box 86, Folder 20)
  - B-rolls index for tapes 49-62, Circa 1995 (Box 86, Folder 21)